Peggy Bacon Papers
Peggy Bacon Papers
1893-2004
Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987.
4.5 linear ft.
Papers of the American author, caricaturist, illustrator, painter. Collection includes correspondence between Bacon and her husband Alexander Brook, as well as that of others; manuscript articles, illustrations, poems, and notebooks; published material including articles, drawings, and newspaper clippings by or about Bacon and Brook; memorabilia, including awards, photographs, and reviews; and miscellany.
148823
Biographical History
Peggy Bacon (1895-1987) was an American author, caricaturist and illustrator.
Margaret "Peggy" Bacon was born in Ridgefield, Connecticut, on May 2 1895, the only child of Charles R. Bacon and his wife Elizabeth, both professional painters, and grew up in an artistic and literary environment. In an interview in 1973 with Paul Cummings for the Archives of American Art, she recalled that "[My parents] were passionate readers of Henry James as fast as his novels came out. Every evening there was reading aloud....[T]here were quantities of books, endless books arriving. And a great deal of charm. They were people of taste. Father was very well-read in French. He spoke French so well that French people mistook him for a Frenchman."
Peggy was largely educated by tutors and governesses until the age of fourteen when she was sent to Kent Place School in Summit, New Jersey. She displayed her artistic talents at an early age and rather than entering college decided to study at the Art Students League in New York City. In 1920 she married fellow student Alexander Brook (with whom she later had two children, Alexander and Belinda) and began her career as artist, writer and teacher.
Peggy Bacon taught at the Corcoran Art School in Washington DC, the Fieldstone School, the Art Students League, Hunter College, and the New School in New York. At the same time, she began exhibiting her pastels, prints, etchings and caricatures in many of the country's major museums. She had had her first one-man show in 1915 and beginning in 1922 she had a show almost every year at various galleries in New York. Like many of her compatriots, she worked for Associated American Artists but did not stay with them long.
Along with her art, Peggy was also a talented writer. She contributed articles, short stories, and witty verse to leading magazines such as The New Yorker, Vanity Fair, and the Saturday Review, including a review in verse of The Women, which "earned [me] two lifelong enemies -- Clare Booth Luce and Henry Luce." Her first children's book, The Lion-hearted Kitten, was published in 1926 and several more quickly followed, as well as illustration work on more than sixty books for both children and adults. In 1952 her first novel, a mystery entitled The Inward Eye, was published and won favorable reviews.
In 1934 Bacon won a Guggenheim Fellowship and a few years later an award from the National Institute of Arts and Letters. She retired to Cape Porpoise, Maine in 1961 where she lived until her death in 1987.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Peggy Bacon Papers consist of artwork originals, artwork reproductions, biographical material, correspondence subject files, legal material, memorabilia and writings.
Artwork originals is a variety of sizes of pencil, ink and watercolor drawings, some done when Bacon was a child.
Artwork reproductions consists of published copies of illustrations she did for her own and other people's writing.
Biographical material includes brief biographies for shows and other purposes as well as curriculum vitae and obituaries.
Correspondence subject files includes Peggy Bacon's correspondence as well as Alexander Brook's correspondence and some of their early correspondence with each other.
Legal material is composed of notes about Peggy Bacon's estate that were made by her daughter Belinda and a copy of Peggy Bacon's birth certificate.
Memorabilia consists of awards and honors, clippings, exhibition announcenments and catalogs, photgraphs, post cards, and a scrapbook.
Writings includes manuscript and published copies of articles, books, poems, reviews and short stories as well as some compositions Bacon wrote as a High School student.
Arrangement of the Collection
General correspondence is arranged chronologically and all other material is arranged alphabetically by type and within type by title where titles exist.
Related Material
has the papers of a number of American artists from the same time period. Please refer to for a complete listing.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Art -- Illustrators; Bacon, Charles R. (Charles Roswell), 1868-1913.; Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987.; Benet, S.V. (Stephen Vincent), 1898-1943.; Bishop, Isabel, 1902-1958.; Bouche, Louis, 1896-1969.; Brook, Alexander.; Cramer, Konrad, 1888-1963.; Duffy, Edmund, 1899-1962.; Fine, Irving, 1914-1962.; Force, Juliana, 1876-1948.; John, Augustus, 1878-1961.; Porter, Katherine Anne, 1890-1980.; Sunami, Soichi, 1885-1971.; White, E.B. (Elwyn Brooks), 1899-1985.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Illustrators, United States.; Painters, United States.; Painting, American.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Women artists, United States.; Women authors, American.; Women painters, United States.; Articles.; Awards.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Drawings (visual works); Juvenilia.; Notes (documents); Obituaries.; Photographs.; Poems.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Authors.; Illustrators.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of Peggy Bacon, 1964.
Inventory
- Artwork, original
  - Booklet The course of the river, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Booklet Day dreams, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Booklet How fairyland disappeared, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Booklet The kittenhood of Maria Bellamy Booker and Teddy, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Booklet verses, 1908 (Box 1)
  - Booklet untitled, 1906 (Box 1)
  - Cut paper silhouette untitled, undated (Box 1)
  - Engravings untitled, undated (Box 1)
  - Print block untitled, undated (Box 1)
  - Sketchbooks, 1906; 1908; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Valentines, 1906; 1922,; undated (Box 1)
  - Watercolor designs for playing cards, undated
  - Miscellaneous sketches, undated (Box 1)
- Artwork, reproductions
  - Book jacket illustrations, 1929; 1958 (Box 2)
  - Published, 1929-1939; 1940-1949,; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
- Biographical material
  - Biographical articles and curriculum vitae, undated (Box 2)
  - Obituaries, 1987 (Box 2)
- Correspondence subject files
  - General correspondence, 1919-1963; 1980-1987,; undated; 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Correspondence between Peggy Bacon and Alexander Brook, 1919-1921; undated (Box 2)
  - The American Academy of Arts and Letters, 1964; 1980 (Box 3)
  - Arms, John Taylor, 1946; 1952,; undated (Box 3)
  - Art Students League of New York, 1925; 1943,; 1980,; 1989 (Box 3)
  - The Arts, 1929 (Box 3)
  - Bacon, Belinda, 1933; 1962,; 1983-1992,; undated (Box 3)
  - Bacon, Charles Roswell and Elizabeth A., 1893; 1952,; undated (Box 3)
  - Bacon, Sophia, 1906 (Box 3)
  - Benet, Stephen Vincent and Rosemary, 1942 (Box 3)
  - Bishop, Isabel, undated (Box 3)
  - Brook, Alexander, undated (Box 3)
  - Brook, Alexander B. (Sandy), 1958; 1981,; undated (Box 3)
  - Brook. Anneke W., 1958-1961; undated; 8 folders (Box 3)
  - Brook, Lisbet and Megan, 1985; undated (Box 3)
  - Bouche, Louis, 1935 (Box 3)
  - Carnegie Institute, 1930 (Box 3)
  - Charles Scribners Sons, 1953; 1955 (Box 3)
  - The Cleveland Museum of Art, 1951 (Box 3)
  - Colt, Amy (Mrs. Charles C.), undated (Box 3)
  - Colt, Charles C. (Chis), undated (Box 3)
  - Colt, Francis Bacon, undated (Box 3)
  - Colt, Henry Francis, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Colt, Mary, 1940; 1941 (Box 4)
  - Colt, Sylvia, undated (Box 4)
  - Cramer, Konrad, undated (Box 4)
  - The Detroit Institute of Arts, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Dreamland A Weekly Caprice, 1905 (Box 4)
  - Duffy, Edmund and Anne Rector, 1925 (Box 4)
  - Dunn, Alan and Mary Petty, 1952 (Box 4)
  - The Evansville Public Museum, 1946 (Box 4)
  - Fantasy and Science Fiction, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Fine, Irving Gifford, 1945 (Box 4)
  - Force, Juliana Rieser, undated (Box 4)
  - The Four Seas Company, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Glennon, Edward, 1962; undated (Box 4)
  - Holmes, John A., Jr., 1957 (Box 4)
  - Houghton Mifflin Company, 1950; 1953 (Box 4)
  - Howard, Cal, 1919 (Box 4)
  - Indiana University Writers Conference, 1958 (Box 4)
  - James, William, 1952 (Box 4)
  - John, Augustus Edwin, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Klitgaard, Georgina, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Le Duc, Arthur Conrad, 1930; 1959 (Box 4)
  - Mandelstam, Abraham, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Metcalf, Addison M., undated (Box 4)
  - Mystery Writers of America, Inc., 1952; 1953 (Box 4)
  - National Academy of Design, 1980 (Box 4)
  - Porter, Katherine Anne, 1958 (Box 4)
  - Pownall, Eleanor, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Richardson, Alice Wilson, undated (Box 4)
  - Riddell, Marjorie, 1953 (Box 4)
  - Sanborn, Robert Alden, 1955 (Box 4)
  - Sanger, William, 1929 (Box 4)
  - Schmidt, Katherine, undated (Box 4)
  - Schnakenberg, Henry E., 1930 (Box 4)
  - Shampanier, Abram August, undated (Box 4)
  - Smith, Grace C. and Beverly, 1948; 1949; undated (Box 4)
  - Smith College of Art, 1954 (Box 4)
  - Soyer, Raphael, 1930 (Box 4)
  - Stern, Louis E., 1930 (Box 4)
  - Summer School of Music and Art Stowe, Vermont, 1964 (Box 4)
  - Sunami, Soichi, 1942 (Box 4)
  - Tucker, Allen, 1930 (Box 4)
  - The Vine Press, 1921 (Box 4)
  - Watson, Forbes, 1952 (Box 4)
  - White, E. B., 1953 (Box 4)
  - Wilson, Edmund, 1940-1943; 1949,; 1951,; 1952 (Box 4)
  - Wilson, William E., 1948 (Box 4)
- Legal material
  - Birth certificate copy, 1920 (Box 4)
  - Notes relating to Peggy Bacon estate, 1988-2004 (Box 4)
- Memorabilia
  - Awards, certficates and honorary degrees
    - Mystery Writers of America, 1954 (Box 4)
    - Moore College of Art, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Moore College of Art, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1952; 1956,; 1963 (Box 4)
  - Clippings
    - Bacon, Peggy, 1919-1985; undated; 5 folders (Box 5)
    - Brook, Alexander, 1923-1946; 1960,; 1978-1981,; undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, undated (Box 5)
  - Exhibition announcements, catalogs and invitations
    - Bacon, Charles Roswell, 1914 (Box 5)
    - Bacon, Peggy and/or Alexander Brook, 1922-1945; 1958-1988,; undated; 3 folders (Box 5)
    - Miscellaneous, 1930; 1972-1980; undated (Box 6)
  - Photographs
    - Family members and trips, undated (Box 6)
  - Postcards
    - Blank postcards of works of art, undated (Box 6)
  - Scrapbooks
    - Clippings and notes, 1925-1928 (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Original art by others, undated (Box 6)
- Writings
  - Articles
    - Character sketches, undated (Box 6)
    - A few ideas, undated (Box 6)
    - God rest ye merry, Christmas, 1947 (Box 6)
    - How to turn a silk purse into a sows ear ir what a tenant can make and do, undated (Box 6)
    - Liberty, undated (Box 6)
    - The life beautiful, undated (Box 6)
    - The lost Eden, 1947 (Box 6)
    - Luminary, undated (Box 6)
    - Mouse about town, undated (Box 6)
    - The peculiarity of Mr. Morton, 1947 (Box 6)
    - The queerest day, undated (Box 6)
    - Small spook, 1960 (Box 6)
    - The sobs of a cynic, undated (Box 6)
    - Temple of Baal, undated (Box 6)
    - Who's who?, undated (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous published articles, 1925-1947 (Box 6)
  - Books
    - Funerealities, 1925 (Box 6)
    - The inward eye, 1952 (Box 6)
  - Poems
    - The bumptious baby, undated (Box 6)
    - Battle hymn or battle him, undated (Box 6)
    - Birthday poems to Alexander Brook, 1923; 1924 (Box 6)
    - Dawn to dusk, undated (Box 6)
    - Hand lettered and illustrated poems, undated (Box 7)
    - A hint to the hunted, undated (Box 7)
    - The mean old alphabet, undated (Box 7)
    - The supersensitive, undated (Box 7)
    - To Cotton Mother, undated (Box 7)
    - To Loogreezy Borgy, undated (Box 7)
    - To Louis that he may temper with sweet temper his temperance, undated (Box 7)
    - To Messy Lena, undated (Box 7)
    - To No. 13 in the Death House I Sing-Sing, undated (Box 7)
    - To Thais from Waif, undated (Box 7)
    - To the menace, undated (Box 7)
    - To Walter wrapped practically in the arms of Morpheus, undated (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous published, 1941; undated (Box 7)
    - Fragments, undated (Box 7)
  - Reviews
    - Call it a day, undated (Box 7)
    - Little bits about big men, 1940 (Box 7)
    - Scenes from the Mesozoic by Clarence Day, 1935 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous published, 1935-1940 (Box 7)
  - School compositions Notes
    - High school essays, 1910-1911; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Short Stories
    - Cat tales, undated (Box 7)
    - The dame and the dime, undated (Box 7)
    - A day's journey, undated (Box 7)
    - The enchanted bar, undated (Box 7)
    - The enchanted man, undated (Box 7)
    - First family, undated (Box 7)
    - Furrier and furrier, undated (Box 7)
    - The mea culpa of Mrs. Reeves, undated (Box 7)
    - The maddening Miss Mantel, undated (Box 7)
    - Mrs. Reeves, undated (Box 7)
    - Pigs in clover, undated (Box 7)
    - Second sight, undated (Box 7)
    - Seven letter word, undated (Box 7)
    - The soft spot, undated (Box 7)
    - Spades & shovels, undated (Box 7)
    - The substitute, undated (Box 7)
    - Uncle Theobald's pet village, undated (Box 7)
    - The wall, undated (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Notes and fragments, undated (Box 7)